Okay Boker Tov בוקר טוב Boker Tov today's
daf דף daf officially lamed-aleph ל"א lamed-aleph we pick up at the
bottom of lamed-amud-aleph ל' עמוד א'. lamed-amud-aleph. We are going to read
again, we're going to start again with the Mishnah משנה. Mishnah. Okay,
the Mishnah's משנה'ס Mishnah's dealing with variations of the case of two
of three brothers, two married to two sisters, one married to a
third woman, and what are the various permutations. So let's take a
look. Shlosha achim shnayim mehem nesuim shtei achayot ve-echad nasui achrit שלשה
אחים שנים מהם נשואים שתי אחיות ואחד נשוי נכרית. Shlosha achim shnayim
mehem nesuim shtei achayot ve-echad nasui achrit. Okay, two brothers married to
two sisters, one married to a third woman. Gerash echad mibaalei ha-achayot
et ishto גירש אחד מבעלי האחיות את אשתו. Gerash echad mibaalei ha-achayot
et ishto. So let's again do this, now for a nice brand
new markers. Okay, we've got Reuven ראובן Reuven and Shimon שמעון Shimon
married to Rachel רחל Rachel and Leah לאה, Leah, and then the
third one here is Levi לוי Levi married to Devorah דבורה. Devorah.
Now, so what happens? So gerash echad mibaalei ha-achayot et ishto גירש
אחד מבעלי האחיות את אשתו. Gerash echad mibaalei ha-achayot et ishto. Now
we'll see what we can how we can use the different markers.
Okay, so he basically divorces Leah לאה. Leah. There's a get גט.
get. Okay, he divorces Leah לאה. Leah. Okay, then what happens? She's
out of the picture.
Gerash echad mibaalei ha-achayot et ishto גירש אחד מבעלי האחיות את אשתו.
Gerash echad mibaalei ha-achayot et ishto. U-met nasui achrit ומת נשוי נכרית.
U-met nasui achrit. So stage number two is Levi לוי Levi dies.
This is stage number one, this is stage number two. Met nasui
achrit מת נשוי נכרית Met nasui achrit u-kinesa ha-migaresh
וכנסה המגרש. u-kinesa ha-migaresh. And then Shimon שמעון Shimon marries Devorah דבורה.
Devorah. That's stage number three. Marries, does yibbum יבום yibbum with Devorah
דבורה. Devorah. That's stage number three. U-kinesa ha-migaresh וכנסה המגרש U-kinesa ha-migaresh
u-met ומת u-met and then Shimon שמעון Shimon dies. So let's take
a look. When Levi לוי Levi died, right, Rachel רחל Rachel or
Shimon שמעון Shimon could have done yibbum יבום yibbum with Devorah דבורה.
Devorah. Wait, correction.
What?
I mean Reuven ראובן Reuven or Shimon שמעון, Shimon, excuse me. When
Levi לוי Levi died, Reuven ראובן Reuven or Shimon שמעון Shimon could
have done yibbum יבום yibbum with Devorah דבורה. Devorah. Okay, Shimon שמעון
Shimon did yibbum יבום yibbum with Devorah דבורה. Devorah. Okay, now when
he did yibbum יבום yibbum with Devorah דבורה Devorah it brought Devorah
דבורה Devorah in and Leah לאה Leah was already out of the
picture. So now when Shimon שמעון Shimon dies, okay, when Shimon שמעון
Shimon dies, so Devorah's דבורה'ס Devorah's totally okay with Reuven ראובן. Reuven.
The problem was Rachel רחל Rachel and Leah לאה. Leah. Leah לאה
Leah was already out of the picture from the moment even before
he died, even before he even married Devorah דבורה. Devorah. So now
that Shimon שמעון Shimon is dead, Reuven ראובן Reuven could go ahead
and do yibbum יבום yibbum with Devorah דבורה. Devorah. So zu hi
she-amru ve-khulan she-metu o nisgarshu זו היא שאמרו וכולן שמתו או נתגרשו,
zu hi she-amru ve-khulan she-metu o nisgarshu, all of these ervot ערוות
ervot if they died or were divorced, tzaroteihen mutarot צרותיהן מותרות. tzaroteihen
mutarot. They're out of the picture and their tzarot צרות, tzarot, Devorah
דבורה Devorah is now mutar מותר mutar to Reuven ראובן Reuven because
Leah לאה Leah was already out of the picture. Now this is
an extreme case. Here's a case where step number one was Leah
לאה Leah was out of the picture, right? So she's out of
the picture way from the beginning. A more interesting case as you
might remember is first he married Devorah דבורה Devorah and then he
divorced Leah לאה. Leah. So there was a time period where those
two were co-wives. Would that have problematized Devorah דבורה Devorah forever to
Reuven ראובן? Reuven? Okay, but in this case it's easy. Leah לאה
Leah was way out of the picture before anything started. Alright, so
that's an easy case. The Gemara גמרא Gemara is now going to
explore some of the middle cases that have not been looked at
the Mishnah משנה. Mishnah. Okay, so let's take a look. And it's
also going to get to this question of whether the Mishnayot משניות
Mishnayot are assuming yesh zika יש זיקה yesh zika or ein zika
אין זיקה. ein zika. So let's take a look. Taama טעמא Taama
says the Gemara גמרא, Gemara, the reason this works
is de-geiraish ve-achar kakh met דגירש ואחר כך מת, de-geiraish ve-achar kakh
met, that first
Shimon שמעון Shimon divorced Leah לאה Leah and then he married Devorah
דבורה Devorah and then he died. So Leah לאה Leah was out
of the picture way before, you know, way before Shimon שמעון Shimon
died and way before the whole picture the whole thing sort of
anyway, even before actually she's always going to be divorced before Shimon
שמעון Shimon dies. Leah לאה Leah was out of the picture before
Levi לוי Levi died. Even before Devorah דבורה Devorah became like relevant
to the conversation, Leah לאה Leah was already out of the picture.
That's why this thing works. Aval met ve-achar kakh geiraish אבל מת
ואחר כך גירש. Aval met ve-achar kakh geiraish. Let's say first Levi
לוי Levi died, okay, and Devorah דבורה Devorah was now in the
picture and then Shimon שמעון Shimon divorced Leah לאה. Leah. Okay, met
ve-achar kakh geiraish מת ואחר כך גירש. met ve-achar kakh geiraish. Maybe
now it's already problematic. As soon as Levi לוי Levi died, even
before there's been yibbum יבום, yibbum, even before there's been yibbum יבום.
yibbum.
Why would that be problematic? Levi לוי Levi has died, if that
were number one that occurred, that Levi לוי Levi had died, what
would happen at this stage, if this was the first thing that
would happen?
Wait, so what are you saying?
Levi לוי Levi died number first. Leah לאה Leah is not yet
divorced. Okay,
what would happen?
So alright, divorce her and then marry Devorah דבורה, Devorah, what should
be the issue? What relationship does Shimon שמעון Shimon right now have
to Devorah דבורה? Devorah?
Any relationship? Zika זיקה. zika.
Okay, he's got the zika זיקה.
zika. Good, we'll use orange for zika זיקה. zika. He's got the
zika זיקה. zika.
So if yesh zika יש זיקה, yesh zika, so now Devorah דבורה
Devorah is a tzarat ervah צרת ערווה tzarat ervah right,
vis-a-vis Reuven ראובן, Reuven, right, so maybe that problematizes Devorah דבורה Devorah
even now, even after divorce and after death, the whole thing. But
so the Mishnah משנה Mishnah is saying the Gemara גמרא Gemara is
saying the Mishnah משנה Mishnah gave an extreme case. Got Leah לאה
Leah out of the picture first thing. If Leah לאה Leah hadn't
been out of the picture first thing, presumably there would be a
problem as soon as Levi לוי Levi died, because this would create
a zika זיקה zika and that would problematize Devorah דבורה Devorah for
Reuven ראובן. Reuven. But so that implies yesh zika יש זיקה. yesh
zika. So let's take a look. Taama de-geiraish ve-achar kakh met aval
met ve-achar kakh טעמא דגירש ואחר כך מת אבל מת ואחר כך.
Taama de-geiraish ve-achar kakh met aval met ve-achar kakh. מת, met, if
the first thing that happened was לוי Levi died, and then לאה
Leah was out of the picture,
אסורה, asura, presumably דבורה Devora would be forbidden to ראובן Reuven because
she would have immediately been sort of צרת ערווה, tsarat erva, צרת
ערווה tsarat erva or quasi צרת ערווה. tsarat erva. So what do
you see? You see רב אשי Rav Ashi זאת אומרת, zot omeret,
from this we can infer, יש זיקה אפילו בתרי אחי, yesh zika
afilu bitrei achai, that there is a זיקה zika even with two
brothers, because as soon as לוי Levi died, ראובן Reuven could have
done יבום yibbum with דבורה. Devora. ראובן Reuven had a זיקה. zika.
So and we know when there are two brothers, it is harder
to say זיקה zika because no one necessarily is going to be
the one that actually going to act on it. So even in
a case of two brothers, this זיקה zika is strong enough to
problematize דבורה Devora that now שמעון Shimon dies, דבורה Devora is a
צרת ערווה tsarat erva or quasi צרת ערווה. tsarat erva. So that
is a pretty strong statement of זיקה, zika, but we got a
problem. If you remember earlier, we said אין זיקה ein zika even
with one brother. So the גמרא Gemara says ולרב אשי קשיא דרב
נחמן, u-le-Rav Ashi kashya de-Rav Nachman, what about what רב נחמן Rav
Nachman said? רב נחמן Rav Nachman learned out אין זיקה אפילו בחד,
ein zika afilu be-chad, even by one brother. So what was רב
נחמן's Rav Nachman proof that אין זיקה ein zika even by one
brother? Now we got to go back and remember that. That was
all the way back yesterday. So what was that case? That was
the משנה Mishna that said you had ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon
and לוי, Levi, right? ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon and רחל Rachel
and לאה, Leah, and here you had לוי Levi
and דבורה. Devora. Okay,
and what did the משנה Mishna say? That משנה Mishna at the
top said
מת אחד בעלי אחיות, met echad ba'alei achayot, that ראובן Reuven
died, וכנס נשי אחות אשתו, ve-kinas neshu achot ishto, and then לוי
Levi did here, I am sorry, not וכנס, ve-kinas, another case is
עשה בה מאמר ומת, asa bah ma'amar u-met, if he did מאמר
ma'amar with רחל Rachel and then he died, okay, so he sort
of brought רחל Rachel into his relationship here, then שמעון Shimon cannot
do יבום yibbum with דבורה Devora because now דבורה Devora has become
like a צרת ערווה tsarat erva after he has done מאמר ma'amar
with רחל. Rachel. So the גמרא Gemara says, why do you have
to do מאמר ma'amar with רחל? Rachel? What? Right, the זיקה zika
should have been a problem. And there is only one relevant brother;
שמעון Shimon is not relevant because he is married to לאה. Leah.
So here it is only one brother and רחל Rachel only created
a problem after מאמר. ma'amar. The זיקה zika alone was not enough
to pull her in. So how come here the משנה Mishna sounds
like even with two brothers the זיקה zika pulls דבורה Devora in?
What is the story? יש זיקה, yesh zika, אין זיקה? ein zika?
One brother sounds like you need מאמר, ma'amar, two brothers sounds like
there is already a problem. So the גמרא Gemara says ולרב אשי
קשיא דרב נחמן, u-le-Rav Ashi kashya de-Rav Nachman,
רב נחמן's Rav Nachman point from here that אין זיקה. ein zika.
אמר לך רב אשי הוה הדין דאף על גב דלא עביד מאמר,
Amar lekha Rav Ashi, hu ha-din de-af al gav de-lo avid ma'amar,
you know what, you are right, this would have been a problem
even without מאמר. ma'amar. The זיקה zika itself would have been a
problem. And ראובן Reuven dies and then לוי Levi dies, you already
have צרת ערווה tsarat erva because of the זיקה, zika, of the
זיקה zika this way,
because of the זיקה. zika. That would have been enough. You are
right. So why did it say he did מאמר ma'amar with רחל
Rachel if the problem existed automatically? Okay, ואף על גב דלא עביד
מאמר נחית מכלל חלצה יבומי לא מיבמה, ve-af al gav de-lo avid
ma'amar, nachis mikhlas khaltza, yibbum lo meyabbu,
דבורה Devora would have had to get חליצה, chalitza, not יבום. yibbum.
The מאמר ma'amar already would have pulled רחל Rachel in. והאי דקתני
מאמר, ve-hai de-katani ma'amar,
so why did it say he did מאמר ma'amar with רחל Rachel
if the problem existed automatically? לאפוקי מבית שמאי דאמרי מאמר קונה קניין
גמור, le-afukei mi-Beit Shammai de-amri ma'amar koneh kinyan gamur,
to tell you that, not that מאמר ma'amar creates the problem, but
that מאמר ma'amar does not solve the problem. According to בית שמאי,
Beit Shammai, maybe if you do מאמר, ma'amar, here we will do
blue for מאמר, ma'amar, now I am getting too caught up with
all my colors, okay, if you did מאמר, ma'amar, maybe that pulled
רחל Rachel in fully and it made her fully לוי's Levi wife
and it pulled her in fully, then לאה Leah could walk out
without חליצה, chalitza, right, because it is a real צרת ערווה. tsarat
erva. Okay, so it told you without מאמר ma'amar רחל Rachel is
already pulled in by זיקה zika and it is a problem, you
cannot do יבום yibbum with לאה, Leah, I mean, I am sorry,
I did not mean לאה Leah to walk out. שמעון Shimon could
not do יבום yibbum with דבורה Devora because רחל Rachel is already
pulled into the equation, but he still needs to do חליצה chalitza
because, you know, the זיקה zika is not דאורייתא, de-oraita, it is
not full. But once with זיקה zika רחל Rachel is pulled in,
שמעון Shimon has to do חליצה chalitza with דבורה, Devora, he cannot
do יבום, yibbum, it creates a problem. Maybe however with מאמר ma'amar
רחל Rachel is fully pulled in and דבורה Devora can walk off
without חליצה, chalitza, maybe like בית שמאי? Beit Shammai? No. קא משמע
לן דלא כבית שמאי. ka mashma lan de-lo ke-Beit Shammai. Okay, so
that is one way of reading these משניות, mishnayot, that מאמר ma'amar
creates, that זיקה zika creates the problem, pulls דבורה Devora in here,
pulls רחל Rachel in here, and the only reason it said מאמר
ma'amar was to tell you it did not make her fully the
wife, that even חליצה chalitza would not be an issue. Now, I
am holding off on the questions because we have to now look
at it in the flip. ולרב נחמן קשיא דרב אשי. u-le-Rav Nachman
kashya de-Rav Ashi. Now רב נחמן Rav Nachman said the opposite.
רב נחמן Rav Nachman said that רחל Rachel is
only a problem because of מאמר. ma'amar. רב נחמן Rav Nachman said
אין זיקה אפילו בחד. ein zika afilu be-chad. Even though לוי Levi
is the only relevant brother here and there is only a one
person זיקה, zika, that is not enough to make רחל Rachel a
problem. He said from this
משנה. Mishna. So if that's true, why does our משנה mishnah *mishnah*
say that לאה Leah, *Leah* has to be divorced first? Even if
לאה Leah? *Leah* isn't divorced first, this זיקה zika. *zika* should not
be meaningful. This זיקה zika *zika* should not pull in דבורה Devorah
*Devorah* and should not create an issue. If it's true that זיקה
*zika* does nothing, that you need מאמר *maamar*. So now we're going
to act it in the flip, because רב נחמן *Rav Nachman* wants
to read all the משניות mishnayot *mishnayos* that אין זיקה ein zika.
*ein zika*. ולרב נחמן קשיא דרב אשי *U'lerav Nachman kashya d'Rav Ashi*,
according to רב נחמן *Rav Nachman* that there's אין זיקה ein zika.
*ein zika* and you needed מאמר *maamar* over here, then how about
here? Why does this sound like if לאה Leah *Leah* wasn't the
first one divorced, we've got a problem because of זיקה *zika*? וכי
תימא הוא הדין דאפילו מת אח"כ גירש צרתה מותרת *V'chi teima hu
hadin d'afilu meis achar kach geiraish tzarasah muteres*. So and if you
say yeah, the משנה mishnah. *mishnah* didn't mean that לאה Leah *Leah*
had to be the first one divorced. It would have worked the
other way. Even if לוי *Levi* first died and then לאה Leah
*Leah* was divorced, that also would have been the same story, okay?
That right, so even if לוי *Levi* died, the זיקה *zika* would
not have been a problem, then לאה Leah *Leah* got divorced and
then he married דבורה Devorah *Devorah*, so ראובן Reuven *Reuven* could go
ahead and do יבום Yibbum *yibum* with דבורה Devorah. *Devorah*. Okay, even
though it gives the scenario that לאה Leah. *Leah* was divorced first,
it doesn't mean that exclusively. That's not the only way this is
true. לוי *Levi* could have died first and זיקה *zika* would not
have been meaningful, and as long as לאה Leah. *Leah* was taken
out of the picture before שמעון Shimon *Shimon* married דבורה Devorah *Devorah*,
everything would have been okay. Have I lost everybody or you guys
with me? Okay, fine. So וכי תימא הוא הדין דאפילו מת אח"כ
גירש צרתה מותרת *V'chi teima hu hadin d'afilu meis achar kach geiraish
tzarasah muteres*. You know what? You're right. It would have been the
same even if לאה Leah *Leah* had not been the one divorced
first. That first לוי *Levi* died and then לאה Leah. *Leah* was
divorced according to רב נחמן *Rav Nachman* who wants to read everything
of אין זיקה ein zika, *ein zika*. Now we're working through everything
with אין זיקה ein zika, *ein zika*. אלא זו למעוטי מאי zu
le-ma'utei mai, *Ela zu l'mautei mai?* So when the משנה mishnah. *mishnah*
says this is the case when they said that if the ערוה
Erva *ervah* is divorced, it's everything's okay, this is the case sounds
like there's another case that wouldn't be true. Okay, so it does
sound like we're not allowing all cases. So what case would not
work in a case of גירוש *geirush*? So what is it coming
to exclude? למעוטי כנס ואח"כ גירש *L'mautei knas v'achar kach geiraish*. Ah,
there's three scenarios. One scenario is the first scenario's what we have
in our משנה mishnah *mishnah*, okay, which is לאה *Leah* is divorced
first and out of the picture first. Okay, that's an easy case.
Okay, and obviously everything's going to be okay. B is לוי *Levi*
dies and then לאה *Leah* is divorced. Okay, so in that case,
okay, לוי *Levi* died and that might maybe created a זיקה *zika*.
And that's the question of יש זיקה yesh zika *yesh zika* or
not. Okay, but we could say you know what? That's also okay,
אין זיקה ein zika, *ein zika*, and as long as לאה *Leah*
gets divorced right away and gets out of the picture, okay, אין
זיקה *ein zika* we're all right. But there's the third possibility, which
is what? לוי *Levi* dies, okay,
שמעון Shimon.
*Shimon* does יבום yibbum *yibum* with דבורה Devorah *Devorah*. Okay, so now
שמעון Shimon *Shimon* right here is married to דבורה Devorah *Devorah* and
לאה *Leah*. And then שמעון Shimon *Shimon* dies.
Okay, in that case, okay, דבורה Devorah, *Devorah* had become like צרת
ערוה tzaras ervah. *tzaras ervah* to ראובן Reuven *Reuven*. I'm sorry, no,
and then excuse me, לאה *Leah* is divorced. Obviously that case wouldn't
work. Okay, then לאה *Leah* is divorced and then and then שמעון
Shimon *Shimon* dies. So in this case, this case basically you had
זיקה *zika* and then לאה *Leah* was out of the picture. In
this case, you had much more than זיקה *zika* then לאה *Leah*
was out of the picture. You had יבום Yibum *yibum* and then
לאה *Leah* is out and then you have death, he dies. Okay,
so there you actually have them married, then לאה *Leah* is divorced
and then she's out of the picture only before שמעון Shimon. *Shimon*
dies. Okay, that case is like, alright, since they were both married
to שמעון Shimon, *Shimon* at the same time, even though she got
out of the picture before he died, it doesn't matter. They were
married to שמעון Shimon, *Shimon* at the same time and that's what
we're excluding. Okay, so let's take a look. It says אלא זו
למעוטי מאי למעוטי כנס ואח"כ גירש *Ela zu l'mautei mai l'mautei knas
v'achar kach geiraish*. That
שמעון Shimon *Shimon* actually married דבורה Devorah *Devorah* and then he divorced
לאה *Leah*. So it wasn't just there was a זיקה *zika* and
then he died. They were actually married and then he divorced and
then he died. So in that case, right, לאה *Leah* only got
out of the picture before he died, but he was married to
both of them at the same time. And that case, even though
she's out of the picture before he dies, it's still a case
of צרת ערוה tzaras ervah *tzaras ervah*. So you might remember that
this is a debate we had before, whether you go by the
time of marriage to determine צרת ערוה Tzaras Erva *tzaras ervah* or
the time of death. הניחא אי סבר לה כרבי ירמיה דאמר *Ha
nicha i savar lah k'Rabbi Yirmiyah d'amar*, that's good if he feels
like רבי ירמיה *Rabbi Yirmiyah* which said way back at the you
know I don't know two-three weeks ago, תברה מי ששנה זו לא
שנה זו *tavrah mi sheshana zu lo shana zu*, divide the משניות
*mishnayos*, the author of one משנה Mishnah *mishnah* is not the author
of the same, there was a problem of Two contradicting משניות. והאי
תנא סבר מיתה מפלת והאי תנא סבר גירושין ראשונים מפילין. ve-hai tanna
sabar mita mappeles ve-hai tanna sabar gerushin rishonim mappilin. And the question
is, is the obligation of יבום Yibum, defined at the time of
death, מיתה מפלת, mita mappeles, makes them fall in front of the
brother-in-law, or is it defined at the time of the marriage? Okay,
so since there's a debate, there's an opinion that says that it's
defined at the time of marriage before the time of death. So
our משנה Mishnah says as long as Leah is divorced, it's okay.
And it seems to say, but not in every case, but in
the case it drew, it didn't, all it meant to exclude was
not that it mattered whether she was divorced and then the brother
died or the brother died and then she was divorced, that wouldn't
matter, אין זיקה. What it meant to exclude was she's got to
be divorced before Shimon marries her. Okay? I don't care, I don't
care here, right, whether first she was divorced and then he died,
or first he died and then she was divorced, but she does
have to be divorced before Shimon married her. Because if Shimon was
married to both at the same time, that creates צרת ערוה. Tzaras
Erva Okay? And don't tell me that as long as he divorced
her before he died, that's good enough. It's not true. He has
to divorce her before he married the other woman. Okay? He can't
be married to both at the same time. All right, so that,
that would be how to read the משנה. Mishnah אלא אי סבר
לה כרבא, ela ei sabar lah kerava, that's fine if there's an
opinion that you go by the time of marriage, but if you
hold like רבא, Rava, דאמר לעולם חד תנא הוא וזו אין צריך
לומר זו קתני, de-amar le-olam chad tanna hu ve-zu ein tzarich lomar
zu katani,
it's all one author of the משנה. mishnah, Again, we won't worry
about exactly which משניות they were dealing with, but basically רבא Rava
is of the opinion that you always go by the time of
death. Okay? So now forget יש זיקה or אין זיקה. We have
a very simple question. If you determine צרת ערוה tzorat ervah. by
the time of death, right, why did we have to give the
scenario that Leah was divorced way up front? There's a much bigger
חידוש. chiddush. The bigger חידוש chiddush is that Shimon marries Devorah and
Leah is divorced only before Shimon dies. That's what רבא Rava would
say. רבא Rava would say that'd be fine. Just get Leah out
of the picture before you die then you're fine. Okay? So why
did we give the scenario that she was out of the picture
at the very first thing? Give a much bigger חידוש, chiddush, right?
Marry Devorah and then divorce Leah. Okay? Why not?
So
זו למעוטי מאי, when our משנה Mishna, says only this case works
by גירושין, gerushin, what's it excluding? Since you actually would say that
there are many cases of גירושין gerushin that would work. על כרחך
כרבי ירמיה סבירא ליה. al korchach kerabbi Yermiyah sevira leh. So it
must be that if you're sort of saying, actually we're not yet
asking how does רבא Rava work, we're saying how does רב זביד
Rav Zebid that say אין זיקה, right? And since he's sort of
saying אין זיקה, so in that case, this order could switch: who
dies and who divorces first. Right? So if that's true, what are
we excluding? We're excluding the case of married and died. But that
would only work if you say
נישואין ראשונים מפילין. nisuin rishonim mappilin. Because if you say you go
by the time of death, there's nothing left to exclude. Okay? According
to רבא, Rava, there seems to be nothing left to exclude. All
cases seem, anytime she's divorced before death seems to work. So therefore
it must be we're not going like רבא. Rava. And it must
be that the case we are excluding is the case when first
he married her and then he died. That case would remain problematic.
Okay? So you gotta, what we have is the following. You have,
I don't know if I'm using the markers too much, now that
I'm confusing people, but you have, okay, you've got
the idea that you go by
נישואין ראשונים. nisuin rishonim. Right? נישואין ראשונים. nisuin rishonim. Okay. So in
that case, right, it goes by they can't be married at the
same time. So there are two scenarios where they're not married at
the same time. First Leah is divorced and then
Levi dies. Okay?
Or Levi dies and then Leah is divorced. Either
way, in either of these cases Shimon is not married to both
of them. Okay? Shimon is not married to both. Which is great,
because that's what we need because you go by נישואין ראשונים. nisuin
rishonim. The only difference here is that if Levi dies first, you
might have זיקה. Does זיקה create a problem? So if you say
אין זיקה, both of these are okay because Shimon isn't married to
them both at the same time. Okay? But here's a third case.
The third case is that basically Shimon marries both. Shimon, you know,
marries Devorah, and then gets
יבום Yibum Devorah, right, whatever, yeah.
And then
Leah is divorced. Okay? In that case, and then he dies. In
that case, right, he's married to both.
he just then divorces before he dies.
Divorces before he dies. Okay? Before he dies. That would only work
if you don't say נישואין ראשונים nisuin rishonim but if you say
מיתה מפלת. mita mappeles. You go by the time of death. Okay,
so now what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s saying is like this: If
you say אין זיקה *ein zika*, so this case also works as
long as he's not married to both of them at the same
time, we don't have to worry about the זיקה *zika*. What's being
excluded? What's being excluded is case number three, when he was married
to both of them and then he divorced before he died. That
still would not be good because we don't say מיתה Missah. מפלטת
*misat mapalet*, we say נשואין ראשונים *nissuim rishonim*. If you were to
פסקן *pasken* מיתה מפלטת *misat mapalet*, he'd be in a bind, 'cause
then all three cases are okay; nothing is left to be excluded.
So since he includes number two because of אין זיקה *ein zika*,
what he's left with excluding is case number three, where they were
married at the same time and she was divorced just before death.
So that's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says. No, the question is
if you פסקן *pasken* number three, what are you left—that's what the
גמרא gemara *Gemara*'s going to ask next. Okay, but we're not yet—but
we're first asking it from the perspective of אין זיקה *ein zika*.
So the גמרא gemara *Gemara* says על כרחך כרב ירמיה סבירא ליה
*al korchacha k'Rav Yirmeya sevira lei*, he must hold by רב ירמיה
*Rav Yirmeya* that we go by נשואין ראשונים *nissuim rishonim* and not
by מיתה *misah*, and we're therefore left, we're able to exclude case
number three. So the גמרא gemara *Gemara* says ולרבא *uleRava*, okay, but
now the real question is if you פסקן *pasken* case number three
works, הניחא אי סבירא ליה כרב אשי *ha nicha ei sevira lei
k'Rav Ashi*, זו היא למעוטי מת בלא גירש *zu hi l'me'utei meis
belo geresh*. So רבא Rava *Rava*, what's left to exclude? All three
of these cases are totally fine because as long as לאה *Leah*'s
divorced before שמעון Shimon *Shimon* dies. So what's the משנה Mishna *Mishnah*
excluding? What case wouldn't work about גירש *geresh*? All these cases work.
So the גמרא gemara *Gemara* says there's one case that wouldn't work.
If he holds like רב אשי *Rav Ashi*, right, רב אשי *Rav
Ashi* holds יש זיקה *yesh zika*, so how's that going to be
an issue? What's one case that won't work? אי סבירא ליה כרב
אשי *ei sevira lei k'Rav Ashi*, זו היא למעוטי *zu hi l'me'utei*,
here's a case you can exclude: מת בלא גירש *meis belo geresh*.
Okay, which is now—it doesn't mean just that שמעון Shimon. *Shimon* died
without divorcing לאה *Leah*, that's obvious, then he's married—that's the case of
צרת ערוה Erva *tzarat ervah*, right? He's married to דבורה Devorah, *Devorah*
and לאה *Leah*, of course. No, it doesn't mean that. It means—don't—let
me just double check רש"י Rashi *Rashi* to make sure I'm saying
this right.
Oh, right. So the case would be that—here would be the scenario
we would be excluding: לאה *Leah* dies—if we פסקן *pasken* יש זיקה
*yesh zika*, okay, לאה *Leah* dies and then שמעון Shimon *Shimon* has
a זיקה *zika*, right? And then you know what happens? שמעון Shimon
*Shimon* dies. Okay, so now if he died before he had a
chance to divorce לאה *Leah*, it was מת בלא גירש *meis belo
geresh*, but it was also before he married דבורה Devorah *Devorah*. Okay,
he didn't marry דבורה Devora *Devorah*, he just—it was just his זיקה
*zika* and then he died. So that זיקה *zika* already—if you say
יש זיקה *yesh zika*, that זיקה *zika* already makes דבורה Devora's *Devorah*,
right, צרת ערוה Erva *tzarat ervah*, and now ראובן Reuven? *Reuven* can't
do anything, right? He can't do יבום Yibum, *yibbum* with דבורה Devora
*Devorah* 'cause at this moment there was already צרת ערוה Erva *tzarat
ervah* because of the זיקה *zika*. So if you פסקן *pasken* any
of these cases where divorce occurred at any time before שמעון Shimon.
*Shimon* died, it works; we all go by the time of death.
Ironically, the one case that doesn't work is the case when his
relationship with דבורה Devora, *Devorah* was the weakest—it was just זיקה *zika*.
But nevertheless, since לאה *Leah* was never divorced, that would be a
problem. Okay, so according to רבא Rava, *Rava*, that's the one case
you exclude. אלא אי סבירא ליה כרב אשי *ela ei sevira lei
k'Rav Ashi*, that works, הניחא אי סבירא ליה כרב אשי *ha nicha
ei sevira lei k'Rav Ashi*, זו היא למעוטי מת בלא גירש *zu
hi l'me'utei meis belo geresh*, okay, because of the זיקה *zika* and
then since there was never a divorce, that זיקה *zika* would have
created a problem. אלא אי סבירא ליה כרב נחמן *ela ei sevira
lei k'Rav Nachman*, but if he פסקן *pasken* like רב נחמן *Rav
Nachman* that says that there is אין זיקה *ein zika*, זו היא
למעוטי מאי *zu hi l'me'utei mai*? There's nothing left to exclude. Any
case of divorce before death works and any case of dying before
divorce works because the זיקה *zika*'s meaningless. על כרחך כרב אשי סבירא
ליה *al korchacha k'Rav Ashi sevira lei*, so רבא Rava *Rava* has
to hold like רב אשי *Rav Ashi*, okay. So if you hold
אין זיקה *ein zika*, you're including these cases and the only case
left to exclude is שמעון Shimon *Shimon* dying—is שמעון Shimon *Shimon* marrying
דבורה Devora's *Devorah* and then divorcing. Okay, that wouldn't work 'cause that's
a divorce after you're married to both. Okay, that's left to exclude.
If you פסקן *pasken* that even that case is okay, any time
she's divorced before death it always works—you go by the moment of
death—then any divorce works. So what's this משנה Mishna *Mishnah* excluding? It's
excluding the case of no divorce, that this זיקה *zika* alone creates
a problem and if he dies with no divorce, even though this
is very weak, since she is not out of the picture even
at the time of death, that's the case that remains a problem.
Okay,
so we worked it out whether you say יש זיקה *yesh zika*
or אין זיקה *ein zika*. Yes, Charlie?
Back to this first one where רב אשי *Rav Ashi* and they
conclude they're excluding the opinion of בית שמאי Beis Shammai?
*Beis Shammai*. Yeah.
Isn't it—isn't it kind of rare? for an אמורא to have to
worry about excluding the opinion of בית שמאי?
Beis Shammai Yeah, that's the point, you know, here we go, בית
שמאי Beis Shammai here seems to be have a much sort of
stronger and viable voice in this מסכת Masechet so far in the
יבום Yibum. cases and he does elsewhere like your ideas, oh let's
just have everybody do חליצה Chalitza in order to satisfy בית שמאי's
Beis Shammai. position, you know, and the whole גוואק Gevack that the
גמרא gemara had a whole discussion before, אירוסי אוסר Erusay Noser and
נישואי אוסר Nissuay Noser according to בית שמאי. Beis Shammai So the
בית שמאי's opinions here seem to carry a bit more weight and
you know and are considered more seriously than elsewhere. So that is
yeah definitely true. Okay, let's go on. וכולן, V'kulan, switching gears now,
okay, and I mean not totally, it's never totally, but it is
a different type of a discussion. וכולן V'kulan שיהיו בהן shehayu bahen
no more brothers and sisters, okay, we're going back way to the
first משנה Mishna about ערוה Erva and צרת ערוה Erva and we've
said one way that they sort of get out of the picture
is if the ערוה Erva, is divorced or has died, okay, before
marriage or but before the other one has married or at least
before the husband dies. That was the question of נישואין Nissuayin or
מיתה. But one way it's dealt with is death is divorce or
death. Here's though another thing which is maybe they're questionably out of
the picture. Now they're not questionably dead. That would be like brain
dead nowadays. Okay, but they could be questionably divorced and they could
be questionably married, okay. So let's say the ערוה erva. may be
in the picture may not be in the picture. What's the story
then? Okay, וכולן V'kulan all these ערוות Ervas שיהיו בהן קידושין או
גירושין בספק, shehayu bahen kiddushin o geirushin b'safek, we don't know if
they were married, right? ראובן Reuven was married to דבורה Devora. and
to maybe רחל, Rachel, okay, and רחל Rachel would be the ערוה
to you know his brother. No רחל Rachel and לאה, just she'd
be the ערוה to his brother. רחל Rachel is ראובן's Reuven, daughter,
alright, and we don't know if שמעון Shimon is married to רחל
Rachel or not.
Is she an ערוה is she part of the equation or not?
How could we not know if she's married to ראובן? Reuven's Either
ספק קידושין safek kiddushin or ספק גירושין. safek geirushin. Okay right, so
that's the issue. Is רחל Rachel in the picture? הרי אלו Harei
elu and in those cases חולצות
צרות chotzot tzarot דבורה Devora, right who definitely is in the picture
חולצות ולא מתייבמות chotzot v'lo misyabmot has to get חליצה Chalitza not
יבום, Yibum. can't do יבום Yibum. because maybe רחל Rachel is in
the picture and she's צרת ערוה and it's אסור assur to do
יבום, yibbum. but you can't you can't walk away because maybe רחל
Rachel isn't in the picture and then you need to do חליצה
Chalitza or יבום. yibbum. So the solution in all those cases of
ספק safek is you do חליצה Chalitza not יבום. yibbum רחל Rachel
you don't have to worry about. רחל Rachel if she's not in
the picture doesn't need anything and if she is in the picture
she's an ערוה, okay. So רחל Rachel isn't the issue. But the
question is what does it do to the status of לאה? It
throws לאה in a ספק safek and therefore לאה needs חליצה Chalitza
not יבום. yibbum כיצד ספק קידושין? Keitzad safek kiddushin? What's a scenario
of ספק קידושין? safek kiddushin? זרק לה קידושין, Zaraka kiddushin, ספק קרוב
לו ספק קרוב לה, safek karov lo, safek karov lah, זו היא
ספק קידושין. zu hi safek kiddushin. Man says הרי את מקודשת לי
בטבעת זו Harei at mekudeshet li b'tabaat zu קח, kach, okay, and
he throws the ring and it falls smack between the two of
them and you don't know whether it's closer to him or closer
to her. Now in the משנה it sounds like it all goes
by who it's closer to. The problem is is that there's not
exactly a קנין kinyan known as it was closer to me. Okay,
so the גמרא gemara sort of speaks about and רש''י Rashi brings
it in there is a קנין kinyan of ד' אמות daled amot
within your ארבע אמות. arba amot. So רש''י describes the scenario that
they're exactly eight amot apart, okay, I don't know if this is
like a model for their future marriage, right, and they keep you
know your own private space. Anyway, and the exact midline is where
their two ד' אמות daled amot the edges of their two ד'
אמות daled amot touch. And you don't know whether it fell in
my ד' אמות daled amot or in her ד' אמות, daled amot,
you know, in the man's or in the woman's. So you don't
know if she ever did a קנין kinyan on the כסף קידושין.
kesef kiddushin. Okay that would be a case of זו היא ספק
קידושין. zu hi safek kiddushin. That's a case of you don't know
if רחל Rachel ever got married to שמעון. Shimon ספק גירושין, Safek
geirushin, now let's say she definitely was married and but you don't
know if she was divorced. Now you would say maybe a similar
case, you threw the גט, get, you don't know if it got
into her side or it didn't get to her side. Interestingly though
the משנה switches gears and not going to deal with a case
of ספק safek but actually a case of a rabbinically פסול pasul
גירושין geirushin which actually is דאורייתא d'oraisa כשר. kasher. And what's that
case? Okay so and therefore it's called ספק safek because rabbinically it's
פסול pasul but really is a different category. Okay so what's that
case? Okay, זו
היא
ספק גירושין?
zu hi safek
geirushin? כתב בכתב ידו ואין עליו עדים, Katav b'ksav yado v'ein alav
edim, so it doesn't have witnesses signing on the bottom of the
גט get but it's in his own handwriting. יש עליו עדים ואין
בו זמן Yesh alav edim v'ein bo zman or it has witnesses
the problem is that it doesn't have a זמן zman which is
a different type of a problem. Or יש בו זמן yesh bo
zman it's got a זמן zman ואין בו אלא עד אחד v'ein
bo ela ed echad and it's not written in his own handwriting,
it doesn't have two witnesses but it has עד אחד. ed echad.
So basically there's three cases: handwritten,
עד אחד, ed echad, or no זמן. zman. But the language by
the way there's interesting in terms of like oral mnemonic right why
don't they just say it simpler? Here's שלשה גיטין פסולין. shelosha gittin
psulin. כתב ידו, Ksav yado, אין בו זמן, ein bo zman, עד
אחד. ed echad. But the the way it's phrased sort of carries
you from one to the next, right, you see the way it's
written it says... like, right, it says like כתב בכתב ידו ואין
עליו עדים, katav bikhtav yado ve’ein alav eidin, יש עליו עדים ואין
בו זמן, yesh alav eidin ve’ein bo zman, יש בו זמן ואין
בו עד אחד, yesh bo zman ve’ein bo ed echad, right? So
it's nice the way sort of you get to all three. It's
a little wordy, but it gets you to all three cases. All
those are a rabbinically פסול גט. pasul gett. יש בו זמן
ואין בו אלא עד אחד. yesh bo zman ve’ein bo ella ed
echad. זהו ספק גירושין. zehu safek gerushin. We're calling it ספק. safek.
It's not really ספק, safek, it’s דאורייתא de'oraita כשר, kasher, דרבנן derabbanan
פסול, pasul but we treat it therefore as this woman is quasi-divorced.
Okay? And therefore you have to go play it safe both ways
as it were, treat her as half and half and you do
חליצה chalitzah and not גירושין gerushin to the other woman. All right.
So now the גמרא gemara points out, why didn't it give the
simple parallel case by גירושין? gerushin? ואילו בגירושין ספק קרוב לו ספק
קרוב לה לא קתני. ve’ilu begerushin safek karov lo safek karov lah
lo katani. It doesn't give that case about, you know, did the
גט get. get into her space or not into her space? So
מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, what's the reason? So the גמרא gemara first
thinks that the reason is that that case actually would not change
her status. You're definitely married to רחל, Rachel, throw her a ספק
גט safek gett which maybe got to her, maybe didn't. Her status
is not ספק, safek he's still definitely married to him. Why would
she still be definitely married to him? This is a principle called
חזקה. chazakah. She has her status quo is his wife. We don't
know if that status quo changed. We don't know if she got
the גט. get So her status quo remains the same and she's
not a ספק גירושין, safek gerushin, she's definitely מגורשת, megureshet, she's definitely
married to the guy.
So then flip it the other way, ספק אירוסין, safek erusin, she's
ודאי vadai not married to him, why don't you keep that status
quo? Right? So that's what the גמרא gemara is going to say.
Let's take a look. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, אשה זו. ishah zo.
Now we're not currently worried about רחל Rachel in the משנה, we're
worried about her co-wife there, potential co-wife דבורה. Devora This woman, בחזקת
היתר לשוק עומדת, bechezkat heter lashuk omedet, right? Before he did the
ספק גט, safek gett, this woman was also, she was a צרת
ערווה. tzarat ervah. She was going to be free to marry anyway.
The same way רחל Rachel was ודאי vadai married and that was
her status quo, דבורה's Devorah, status quo was ודאי vadai not having
to worry about יבום. yibbum. Okay? ומספק אתה בא לאוסרה. umisafek attah
ba le'osrah. Now you're coming to say, oh wait, maybe רחל Rachel
was divorced and therefore you can't go ahead and marry somebody else,
you need חליצה chalitzah and not יבום. yibbum, אל תאסרנה מספק. al
te'asrennah misafek. Don't do that out of doubt. Let her keep her
status quo. Okay, so a funny way of saying it like, you
know, you're not entitled, she has a right. Okay, but anyway the
point is her status quo, keep everybody with their status quo. All
right, so ספק גט safek gett would not affect
רחל's Rachel status. Now it's an interesting question, would the גמרא gemara
really say that that רחל Rachel now could, you know, what would
be I guess the consequence? Well actually it's not such a bad
consequence because she still couldn't marry another man. Anyway, the question is
is the גמרא gemara being prepared to say that even in terms
of רחל Rachel that we're not worried about רחל's Rachel status? That's
the status quo, or at least in terms of דבורה Devorah, the
co-wife where, you know, it's much weightier about the question about the
married woman's status, right? You know, because that's like a whole question
of adultery and so on. You know, the question about the יבום
yibbum. aspect of marrying some other guy is a less weighty question.
But the גמרא Gemara anyway is not really making that distinction, it's
basically saying just keep everything at the status quo. So ספק גט
safek gett would not change דבורה's Devorah, status. So the גמרא Gemara
says if that's true, say the same thing about a ספק קידושין,
safek kiddushin. keep everything at the status quo. The גמרא Gemara says
like this, אי הכי בקידושין נמי נימא, ee hachi bekiddushin nami neima,
אשה זו בחזקת היתר ליבם עומדת. ishah zo bechezkat heter leyavam omedet.
This woman דבורה, Devorah you know, before he might have maybe married
רחל, Rachel, דבורה Devorah could have had יבום yibbum, with the brother-in-law.
Okay?
ומספק אתה בא לאוסרה. umisafek attah ba le'osrah. Now you're coming to
say, oh wait, maybe her status
changed, maybe the guy married רחל Rachel as well. אל תאסרנה מספק.
al te'asrennah misafek. Don't change her status from ספק, safek, let her
remain allowed to do יבום. yibbum, Okay? So basically in either case
keep the status quo. גמרא Gemara, says no, התם לחומרא. hatam lechumra.
We're being מחמיר. machmir. Okay, because what are the cases? If you
don't know if the husband married רחל, Rachel, so maybe this woman,
right, דבורה, Devorah right, she had been allowed to do יבום, yibbum,
maybe now she should be forbidden to do יבום. yibbum, Okay? So
that's a serious question, right? Maybe it's going to be a case
about an issue of איסור אשת אח, issur eshet ach, חיוב כרת,
chiyuv karet, and so on. So even though the status quo would
say let her do יבום, yibum we're going to say, oh, just
play it safe, don't do יבום, yibum do חליצה. chalitzah. It's true,
the status quo should say you could still go ahead and do
יבום, yibum, play it safe. Okay, in principle you're right, we're going
דרבנן derabbanan play it safe, don't do יבום, yibum do חליצה. chalitzah.
The other case, right, basically
where ספק גט, safek gett דבורה Devorah, was free to marry some
other guy. Okay? So we're saying and now we're saying, okay, we
don't know if that status changed, go ahead and marry another guy.
We're not going to ask that you do חליצה. chalitzah. Well, why
don't we play it safe there and say don't marry another guy
until you do חליצה? chalitzah? Well, first thing to appreciate is that
the weight of that is much less. Marrying another guy without חליצה
chalitzah is a simple לאו, lav, it's not like an איסור כרת.
issur karet. But the גמרא Gemara's anyway is going to get to
that, but at this stage the גמרא Gemara says in principle you're
right, both cases go to status quo, but this case where maybe
he married רחל Rachel we're not going to... allow her to do
ייבום yibbum because even though you're right in principle, okay, let's play
it safe. ייבום yibbum's a pretty scary thing if you're not allowed
to do it, so just go ahead and do חליצה. chalitza. So
the גמרא Gemara says התם לחומרא, hasam lachumra, we're being מחמיר. machmir.
האי חומרא דאתי לידי קולא. Hai chumra d'ati lidei kula. The גמרא
Gemara says that's a חומרא chumra that's just going to lead to
a leniency. What's the leniency? זימנין דאזיל הוא ומקדש לה לאחותה, Zimnin
d'azil hu umekadesh lei lachotah, so I guess I'll
just erase all of this.
Okay,
so here you have the case of ספק קידושין. safek kiddushin? What's
the case of ספק קידושין? safek kiddushin
שמעון Shimon is married to דבורה Devorah.
and
maybe he's married to, okay, רחל. Rachel. Okay, so in this type
of a case, דבורה Devorah. status quo before that act happened was,
what was it? מותר ליבם, mutar l'yabam, right? Okay,
now this creates a ספק. safek Okay, so this creates a ספק.
safek Does that really, is that really going to impact it? They
say, you know what, just go ahead and play it safe. You
don't want to have somebody doing ייבום yibbum to דבורה Devorah, if
she real, if she really has become אסור. assur. All right, in
principle she should be able to keep her status quo, and you
know, and ראובן Reuven here should be able, should be able to
do ייבום yibbum to דבורה, Devorah but you know, that's, that's pretty
dangerous. So in principle you're right, but just do חליצה. chalitza.
If שמעון was married to like לאה then...
Forget who he's married to, right?
ראובן, Reuven I'm sorry, רחל Rachel is ראובן Reuven... daughter, okay, he's
רחל Rachel's father, okay. We're not dealing with sisters anymore, okay?
So in this case, if שמעון had married רחל, Rachel, דבורה Dvora.
out of the picture. But if not, he can't. So why would
you say okay, but status quo, go ahead and do ייבום yibbum
with דבורה. Dvora, No, you know in principle you're right, but it's
pretty scary, so let's do חליצה. chalitza. We'll be מחמיר. machmir. So
the גמרא Gemara says that's a חומרא דאתי לידי קולא. chumra ha'ati
lidei kula. What's the חומרא דאתי לידי קולא? chumra ha'ati lidei kula?
Think about the following case. Okay, it says like this: הא חומרא
דאתי לידי קולא הוא, ha chumra d'ati lidei kula hu, זימנין דאזיל
הוא ומקדש לה לאחותה קידושי ודאי. zimnin d'azil hu umekadesh lei lachotah
kiddushei vadai.
Okay,
so let's say he goes along and
marries, let me just look back here.
Right, so basically, so let's say after having done a ספק קידושין
safek kiddushin, to רחל, Rachel, he went ahead and now here's where
לאה comes into the picture. He did a ודאי קידושין vadai kiddushin
to לאה. Okay, that just,
he went ahead, he didn't know if the money got to רחל
Rachel or not, he decided I'm going to go ahead and marry
לאה. He did. Wait, no, he hasn't slept with her yet, we're
going to figure out what the consequences of that are. If he
really is married to רחל, Rachel, that was meaningless. If he wasn't,
that works. Okay, so he went ahead, he didn't ask anybody, that's
what he did. אי נמי, Inami, says the גמרא, Gemara okay,
one minute. ואי נמי זימנין דאתא אחר ומקדש לו לדידה קידושי ודאי.
Veinami zimnin d'ata acher umekadesh lo l'didah kiddushei vadai. Or another scenario,
okay, somebody else came, I don't know, here we'll have our friend
ברק Barak again, and he's going to go ahead and marry רחל.
Rachel. Okay, so if let's say after this act of ספק קידושין,
safek kiddushin. some people started doing weird stuff, okay, and they did
other קידושין kiddushin, in the picture, so what will the consequence be
now if we say to ראובן Reuven do חליצה chalitza don't do
ייבום? yibbum? If we say to ראובן Reuven do חליצה chalitza to
דבורה, Dvora. don't do ייבום, yibbum, in principle we could go by
the status quo, דבורה Dvora remains מותר, mutar, she should remain single,
we should go by the status quo, right? But we're going to
say play it safe, just do חליצה. chalitza. So חליצה chalitza sends
the message that, that, what? That, what does חליצה chalitza send the
message?
That ייבום yibbum could
have
been possible, that he, wait, did I say this right?
This is קידושי ספק, kiddushei safek, so, I'm,
wait,
hold
on. Wait, hold on. Right, if
ראובן...
Reuven
Right, right, right, so it's not that ראובן Reuven... is doing חליצה,
chalitza, that's funny because you know, people don't see the absence of
ייבום, yibbum, they see the presence of חליצה. chalitza. So we'll get
to the fact that he did חליצה chalitza in a minute, because
that sends the opposite message. Doing חליצה chalitza sends the message that
רחל Rachel is not married. Okay, but that's not the גמרא Gemara
initial step. The initial step is, if we don't let ראובן Reuven
do ייבום, yibbum, okay, the absence of doing ייבום. yibbum. If we
don't let him do ייבום, yibbum, then that sends the message that
רחל Rachel is married, right? If you focus on the fact that
he said I want to do ייבום yibbum and they say you're
not allowed, okay, that would send the message to people that רחל
Rachel is married to שמעון. That's why he's not allowed. Oh, if
רחל Rachel's married to שמעון, then ברק Barak will assume my marriage
didn't work and לאה will assume the marriage didn't work. But in
principle, since we keep status quo, she's actually not married to שמעון,
she's married to ברק Barak or he's married to לאה. Okay, so
we'll send a problematic message because the message will be that this
worked when in principle it didn't work and there's... And there will
be real consequences from that. Yes. You had a question? No. Okay.
Wait, no, no, let's read that.
Okay. וכיון דאתו למימר לצרי ליבומי, v’keivan de-atu le-meimar l’tzarei l’yabumei, since
you're sending the message don't do יבום yibum with דבורה, Dvora. אמרי,
amri, the only reason you can't do יבום yibum, is it must
be the קידושין kiddushins worked, the קמא קידושין, kama kiddushin, the קידושין
kiddushin that שמעון did to רחל Rachel worked, and that's why we
won't allow יבום, yibum, and therefore this stuff we don't have to
worry about.
Okay. ודבציר לאו קידושין, ud'batsar lav kiddushin, but that's actually not true,
it's actually the opposite, and there'll be terrible consequences. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says one minute, it's not really the absence of
יבום yibum we've got here. We have a presence of חליצה. chalitzah.
And if anything, that sends the right message. Okay, if he is
doing חליצה chalitzah to דבורה, Dvora right, then that sends the message
that he's not married to רחל. Rachel. All right, you wouldn't do
חליצה chalitzah if רחל Rachel was in the picture. So the חליצה
chalitzah actually sends the right message, so that's okay.
Why? Shouldn't do חליצה chalitzah if you want to do יבום yibum,
with her.
I understand. But the possibility of חליצה chalitzah is only possible if
רחל's Rachel out of the picture. So that and that exactly reflects
the facts. The status quo is that רחל Rachel is single, that's
the real principle in הלכה. halacha. So what we're saying is this
is a no-cost חומרא. chumra. Why is it a no-cost חומרא? chumra?
The הלכה halacha is that status quo רחל Rachel is not married
to שמעון after a ספק safek קידושין. kiddushin That's the הלכה. halacha.
Go ahead and do חליצה, chalitzah, okay, it'll what message will it
send? It'll send the message that רחל's Rachel out of the picture.
Okay. The only thing is we're not going to let him do
יבום, yibum. but that's not a problematic message, people don't see the
absence of יבום, yibum, they see the presence of חליצה, chalitzah, and
that actually sends the accurate message.
And the other two קידושין kiddushin both worked.
And these things will work, right.
Okay, let me just finish and then take the question. וכיון דקמצרכת
חליצה, v'keivan de-kamatzreikh chalitzah, since you're demanding חליצה, chalitzah, מידי ידיע דחומרא
בעלמא הוא, midei yada d'chumra b'alma hu, then it's perfect, people know.
Okay, they didn't let him do יבום yibum. but they demanded חליצה,
chalitzah, they saw the חליצה, chalitzah, so the right message got sent.
The demand of חליצה chalitzah maybe sent the primary message that this
was not did not work. You go by you go by status
quo, and the fact that we in principle could have he could
have done יבום, yibum. that's okay, that's a חומרא, chumra, but no
bad message is sent. People see the חליצה, chalitzah, which therefore which
therefore sends the right message that רחל Rachel is not married to
שמעון. Now, question.
Are we elevating חליצה chalitzah to an active positive act rather than
just a default position?
Yeah, well it is an act. I mean, it's something you do.
You go ahead and it's a default position where you can't do
יבום.
yibum, No, you have to do the act of חליצה, chalitzah, right,
and that's necessary, right, in order to free the woman from the
relationship, she needs an act of חליצה. chalitzah. חליצה chalitzah is not
the absence of יבום, yibum חליצה chalitzah is the actual act. The
taking off of the shoe, the spitting, the whole thing.
Right, but that's not it's we're almost
implying here it's not only done when you don't want to do
יבום. yibum.
Well, it's also done when we don't let you do יבום. yibum,
In principle, he could do יבום, yibum that's true, I concede the
point, רחל Rachel really is status quo out of the picture. We're
going to be מחמיר machmir and not allow it, but we're still
going to demand חליצה. chalitzah. Okay, and that'll and that'll send the
right message.
I may have had a misunderstanding but prior I thought that the
the man has the option to do יבום yibum, or חליצה. chalitzah.
He does. Until the rabbis get involved and say there's some cases
we won't let you do יבום.
yibum But is חליצה chalitzah as an independent positive
There are times when the rabbis because of like all range of
types of חומרות, chumros, אחזו זיקוקתו achozo zikukaso and all these types
of things, don't allow יבום, yibum. but there's still a דאורייתא de-oraita
connection there and the only way that that can be addressed if
we're not allowing יבום yibum. is through חליצה. chalitzah. Okay. All right.
So that's what the גמרא Gemara says. You know what? You're right.
We go by status quo. But this case is a no-cost חומרא,
chumra, okay, because he basically does חליצה, chalitzah, which is consistent with
רחל Rachel not being in the picture, and the only thing is
we're not letting him do יבום, yibum but that doesn't that doesn't
undermine the fact that the basic message is is that רחל Rachel
is is not married. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says אי הכי
גירושין נמי לתני, i hachi gerushin nami lisni, so why not go
back to the case of גירושין? gerushin, What would be the case
of a ספק גירושין, safek gerushin? not the case of the משנה,
but the parallel case of a ספק גירושין? safek gerushin The parallel
case of a ספק safek גירושין gerushin? where you would go by
the status quo is you have שמעון is definitely married to, you
know, רחל Rachel and דבורה, Dvora. okay, and then there's a questionable
גט. get Okay, so there's a question here is
was she taken out of the picture with a גט? get. Okay,
so in that case, the status quo of דבורה Dvora? was, okay,
and again ראובן Reuven who is רחל's Rachel father,
okay, so in that case the status quo of דבורה Dvora before
the questionable גט get, was מותרת לשוק. muteres lashuk. Right? That she
wouldn't have to worry because she was a צרת ערוה. And in
principle we're saying be- And now that's in principle, you keep the
status quo, you allow her to be מותרת לשוק, muteres lishuk, and
you don't add, "maybe it changed and maybe you have to, you
know, רחל's Rachel out of the picture and maybe he has to
do חליצה." chalitzah. We're not going to ask him to do חליצה.
chalitzah. Okay? So the גמרא Gemara says, "Why not? Have him do
חליצה. chalitzah. Let it be a חומרא." chumra. So now we're going
to see what the consequences of the negative message that will be
sent by the חליצה. chalitzah. אי הכי? ei hachi? גרושין geirushin נמי?
nami? ליתני וליצרך חליצה? lisni velitzrach chalitzah? Why not have a חומרא
chumra there and make him do חליצה? chalitzah? ומידי דחומרא בעלמא הוא?
umidi dechumra bealma hu? And people will know the משנה said only
by a ספק safek גט get which was really a דרבנן de-rabonon
פסול גט. pasul gett, Right? The first statement that רבא made is
since the משנה did not have the parallel of a real ספק
safek, by a גט get of whether it got to her or
not, that case you would go by status quo. You would not,
you would ignore the גט get, and you'd go by status quo.
So the question is, well why not have a חומרא? chumra? So
we're going to have to explain how a חומרא chumra here is
going to come at a cost. Okay? So here we're going, according
to רבא, we keep the status quo and we let דבורה Devora.
go ahead and marry, we don't demand anything. What will be the
cost of a חליצה? chalitzah? How will that be interpreted? So the
גמרא Gemara says, still go ahead and do a
חליצה. chalitzah. וליצרך חליצה. velitzrach chalitzah. ומידי דחומרא בעלמא היא. umidi dechumra
bealma hi. People will know it's a חומרא. chumra. Right? How will
people know it's a חומרא? chumra? I don't know, because you're not
allowing ייבום. yibbum. So somehow they'll know it's a חומרא. chumra. Of
course, I don't know how you send the message that you didn't
allow ייבום. yibbum. People see חליצה chalitzah and they assume that there
was a real relationship. So if he were to do חליצה, chalitzah,
people would say, "Oh, if he did חליצה, chalitzah, the only reason
he's doing חליצה chalitzah is that רחל Rachel must be divorced." And
then רחל Rachel can go ahead and marry another man. Right? I
mean she can marry another man because שמעון's already dead. But let's
say she married a man before she died. Okay? You can figure
out the consequences. If he does חליצה, chalitzah, it sends the message
that רחל's Rachel divorced, and that's not the case. In a ספק
safek גט, get. it's a status quo and we assume that she's
still married to שמעון. Okay? So here חליצה chalitzah sends the right
message, that רחל's Rachel out of the picture. Here, חליצה chalitzah sends
the wrong message. It sends the message that רחל Rachel is out
of the picture when she really is in the picture. Okay? So
the גמרא Gemara says like this.
So, "נו אם אתה אומר חולצת משבא מת?" no im ata omer
choletzes misheba meis? It's not sending the right message. If you do
a חליצה, chalitzah, people will assume that רחל's Rachel out of the
picture and you could do ייבום. yibbum. So the גמרא Gemara says,
"הכא נמי אם אתה אומר חולצת משבא מת?" hacha nami im ata
omer choletzes misheba meis? So here too, if you do חליצה chalitzah
with דבורה, Devora? he'll come to do ייבום yibbum with דבורה. So
the גמרא says, "Alright, but big deal. Here he really could do
ייבום yibbum with דבורה." Okay? "וליתיבם ולית בה כלום." veyisyabem velis bah
klum. Okay, so let it be ייבום. yibbum. Meaning we don't want
to, we're מחמיר, machmir, but big deal if you make a mistake.
Meaning here the message of חליצה chalitzah is a message that implies
that ייבום yibbum might be possible. Okay? And here ייבום yibbum really
is possible. So doing חליצה chalitzah has a very low cost. You're
not sending the wrong message to people, and if he somehow gets
confused and chooses to do ייבום yibbum with דבורה, big deal. Basically
רחל Rachel really wasn't in the picture anyway. Here though, רחל Rachel
really is in the picture because of status quo. א, alef, חליצה
chalitzah sends the wrong message.
ב, beis, even if people understand that it's somehow a חומרא chumra
because they see we wouldn't allow ייבום, yibbum, we demanded חליצה. chalitzah.
Nevertheless, once you're doing חליצה, chalitzah, חליצה's chalitzah one step away from
doing ייבום, yibbum, and here would really be a major problem because
here רחל's Rachel in the picture and ייבום yibbum is a very
serious issue of ערוה. Okay? So the basic simple explanation is we
do go by status quo. Here we can demand חליצה chalitzah because
it's consistent with the right status. Here we're not going to allow
חליצה chalitzah because it actually is sending the opposite message and allowing
for the exact wrong type of behavior. Alright, so let's see where
the גמרא goes with this.
Okay, so the גרושין geirushin
sends a message of divorced. Yes, גרושין, geirushin, divorce. Okay? We're not
allowing... We're not allowing חליצה... chalitzah well what we're actually doing is
we're not requiring חליצה. chalitzah We're letting you go by the status
quo because the ספק safek. גט get? you go by status quo.
רחל's Rachel still married and we're letting דבורה walk off without anything.
We're actually being much more lenient here. We're not requiring חליצה chalitza
as a stringency because to require חליצה chalitza? would be counterproductive. Okay?
It would send the exact wrong message. And therefore we're going to
better to actually let not be מחמיר. machmir. You know, חומרות chumeros
don't often come at cost. Okay, so that's the issue. Now the
גמרא says like this. Okay. So the basic principle of רבא's whole
idea is you keep the חזקה. chazakah. Whether married or divorced and
there's a ספק, safek. in principle you go by the חזקה. chazakah.
איתיביה אביי. isivei Abaye. אביי Abaye asked, "In this case
divorce you're saying is a ספק."
safek
Walks off. The ספק, safek, the only ספק safek. גט get of
the משנה is really a פסול גט, pasul gett. a דרבנן de-rabonon
פסול pasul, גט. gett A real ספק safek, גט gett has no
consequence. We go by status quo. Okay, so the גמרא says like
this. איתיביה אביי. isivei Abaye. So
אביי Abaye asked, "Here's a case. נפל הבית עליו ועל בת אחיו,
ואין ידוע איזה מהם מת ראשון."
Nafal habayis alav v'al bas achiv v'ein yadua eizeh
meihem meis rishon.
So basically
ראובן... Reuven, ראובן Reuven is married to, where am I going to
draw this? I'll draw it right here. Okay,
so ראובן Reuven.
and שמעון'ס Shimon's
what's the case?
נפל הבית עליו ועל בת אחיו. nafal habayis alav ve'al bas achiv,
Hold on.
I know it's his niece. Hold on a minute. To
his daughter? Right. Okay fine.
So שמעון is married to, well, we'll do it the same way
we did it before. רחל Rachel is ראובן'ס Reuven's daughter. Okay. So
here שמעון is married to רחל. Rachel. Okay, that's ראובן'ס Reuven's daughter,
that's בת אחיו. bas achiv. Okay? ראובן, Reuven ראובן Reuven is רחל'ס
Rachel's father.
רחל'ס Rachel's father. That's the case. Okay. So basically רחל Rachel is
an ערווה erva to ראובן. Reuven Okay. And שמעון is married to
רחל, Rachel, and he's also married to דבורה. Right then he and
רחל Rachel go on a vacation, they didn't invite דבורה,
so and the house fell on them and they both died.
Okay. So now ראובן Reuven, can go ahead and do יבום yibum
with דבורה. רחל'ס Rachel's out of the picture. Of course, is she
out of the picture? Who died first? If רחל Rachel died first,
this by the way is assuming מיתה מפולת, misa mapeles, talk about
מפולת mapeles for those who know. Anyway, if רחל Rachel died first
and it matters what happens at the time of death, then when
שמעון died then only דבורה was in the picture and then he
can do יבום. yibum But if שמעון died first then it was
צרת ערווה tzaras erva and he can't. So what do you do?
נפל הבית עליו ועל בת אחיו Nafal habayis alav v'al bas achiv.
ואין ידוע איזה מהם מת ראשון. ve'ein yaduah eizeh meihem meis rishon.
You don't know which one.
צרתה חולצת ולא מתייבמת. Tzarasa choletzes v'lo misyabemes. So what are you
left to do? In a case of ספק, safeik, you do חליצה
chalitza not יבום. yibum. ראובן Reuven. does it with דבורה. But now
let's apply רבא'ס Rava's logic about the status quo. אמאי? Amai? הכא
נמי נימא. Hacha nami neima. So before the house fell down, what
was דבורה'ס Dvora's status quo? דבורה'ס Dvora's status quo was מותרת לשוק,
mutteres lashuk, right? That was her status quo, right?
Yes, everybody understand? Yeah. Okay. So let's let her retain her status
quo and let her go ahead and walk away. Okay, so אמאי?
Amai? הכא נמי נימא אשה זו בחזקת היתר לשוק עומדת ומספק אתה
בא לאוסרה אל תאסרנה מספק. Hacha nami neima isha zu b'chezkat heter
lashuk omedes umisafek ata ba l'osra al teaserena misafek. So why are
you going to demand חליצה? chalitza וכי תימא הכא נמי לחומרא? V'chi
teima hacha nami l'chumra? No, חומרא דאתי לידי קולא הוא. chumra d'asi
lidei kula hu. שמא תאמר חולצת מתייבמת, shema tomar choletzes misyabemes, right?
ראובן Reuven. is going to think, oh, if I do חליצה chalitza
to דבורה I could do יבום yibum? to דבורה. Okay and the
status quo actually is that she is... the fact that she's מותרת
לשוק mutteres lashuk means that she's an ערווה erva to ראובן, Reuven
right? So חליצה chalitza is very dangerous here because in principle she's
a real ערווה erva to ראובן. Reuven. She's really אסור assur to
ראובן. So חליצה chalitza in a case will... could lead to יבום
yibum. just like here חליצה chalitza could lead to a case of
יבום yibum when she's really אסור. assur. When she's really אסור assur
to ראובן you don't want her to do חליצה chalitza. because that
could lead to יבום. yibum. So the same could be true here.
The status quo is that she's really אסור assur to ראובן. So
how could we allow חליצה chalitza, to lead to יבום? yibum.
So the גמרא says... he'll get confused or something like that.
So the גמרא says like this, or other people will look at
a similar case: גירושין דשכיחי גזרו בהו רבנן. Gerushin d'shchichi gazru bohu
rabbanan. מפולת דלא שכיחי לא גזרו בהו רבנן.
Mapoles d'lo shchichi lo
gazru bohu rabbanan.
So since the whole thing is, it's funny because we start by
we want to do a חומרא chumra of חליצה. chalitza But are
we afraid of the cost of the חומרא? chumra? So here we're
not afraid of the cost of the חומרא. chumra. This case is
so rare, so how many times is it going to happen? If
we say do חליצה, chalitza. you know, oh, one of those times
instead of doing חליצה chalitza somebody's going to do יבום. yibum This
case barely ever happens. So here we can go ahead and be
מחמיר machmir and demand חליצה. chalitza. These types of cases of divorce,
divorce sadly is more common. So we can't allow in this case
חליצה chalitza because one of these cases somebody will wind up doing
יבום and that's a real cost. Okay.
Do we have a case someone you know was
חושש choshesh for two of them? I don't care. Yes, yes. אינמי
גירושין דקאימי ערווה דקמוכח וקא צרכה חליצה אמרו קמו רבנן בגיטה דגיטא
מעליא הוא.
Inami gerushin d'kaimi erva d'kamuchach v'ka tzaracha chalitza amru kamu rabbanan b'gita
d'gita maalya hu.
Okay,
here you understand how this could lead to חליצה. chalitza, Why? Because
in this case people will say look, רחל Rachel is around. So
why is he allowed to... why did he do חליצה chalitza to
דבורה? Isn't רחל Rachel here? Doesn't that make דבורה צרת ערווה? tzaras
erva? So the fact that they're saying חליצה, chalitza? it must be
that they looked into the case and they realized that רחל Rachel
was really divorced else there would not have been חליצה chalitza because
people are going to wonder, what's the story with this חליצה? chalitza?
So people will say it must be the rabbis realized רחל Rachel
is really divorced and that's why the חליצה chalitza is. And if
that's true that's going to lead to negative con... you know, bad
consequences. People will draw the exact wrong conclusions. Okay. So they will
say or he'll come up to do יבום. Okay. So he says
וקא צרכה
חליצה אמרו קמו רבנן בגיטה דגיטא מעליא הוא ופסלו ליבומי לצרה. v'ka
tzaracha chalitza amru kamu rabbanan b'gita d'gita maalya hu v'paslu l'yibumei l'tzara.
And then that'll lead to, right, doing יבום. How? Because people will
say how could you do
חליצה? chalitza, Must be that רחה Rakha actually got a good גט.
get. Oh, okay, so then they'll lead to doing יבום with דבורה.
Okay, so that's a big problem. But מפולה, mapola, מי קמו בי
רבנן במפולה? mi kamu bei Rabbanan b'mapola?
But if the building fell on him in this case, they'd say,
oh, what, why is he doing חליצה chalitza with דבורה? First of
all, they won't ask the question so much because רחה Rakha isn't
in the picture. So they're not going to start wondering like, you
know, what happened to רחה, Rakha, you know, this or that and
the other, and that and the other thing is that people will
actually forget what I just said because that's not my thinking. Anyway,
the point is that people won't say the Rabbis, you know, went
ahead and figured out, you know, when the building fell. That's not
something that's normally in the Rabbinic purview. Determining whether a גט get
is good or not is something in the Rabbinic purview. Determining who
the building fell on first tends not to be. So since here
it's about a building, people will not say, oh, because it's a
חליצה, chalitza they must have known what order things happened. They can,
they'll more understand that you're doing a חליצה chalitza by ספק safek
and they won't act on it. Whereas here, they'll assume that you're
doing a חליצה because you figured out the case and we're afraid
that they will, and therefore he walks free because the חליצה comes
at too big of a cost. Okay, we will stop here. Okay,
that's hard.